<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proceedings of the army under the command of Sir Thomas Fairfax From ... Containing the story of the Club-men, and relief of Taunton. Wherein is expressed the propositions of the Club-men, and Sir Thomas Fairfax his answer unto them. Sent from Mr Bowles (Chaplain to Sir Thomas Fairfax) to a friend of his in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91051</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899257</idno>
  <idno type="VID">152964</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248522637</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3573A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC P1047</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899257</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99899257e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152964)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2337:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proceedings of the army under the command of Sir Thomas Fairfax From ... Containing the story of the Club-men, and relief of Taunton. Wherein is expressed the propositions of the Club-men, and Sir Thomas Fairfax his answer unto them. Sent from Mr Bowles (Chaplain to Sir Thomas Fairfax) to a friend of his in London.</title>
                  <author>Bowles, Edward, 1613-1662.</author>
                  <author>Gellibrand, Samuel, d. 1675, publisher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 v.   [Numb. 1] (first of July to the sixth)-Numb. 7. (eighth of August to the fifteenth of the same.).</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Samuel Gellibrand, July 9,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London [England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written and edited by Edward Bowles.</note>
                  <note>On titlepage above imprint: "Published according to order."</note>
                  <note>Titles of first four issues fluctuate.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Rylands University Library.</note>
                  <note>Numbering begins with Numb. 2.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Newspapers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:1"/>
                  <p>THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE Army under the Command OF Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the first of <hi>July</hi> to the sixth.</p>
                  <p>Containing the Story of the CLUB-MEN, And Relief of TAUNTON.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is expressed The <hi>Propositions</hi> of the CLUB-MEN, And Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX His <hi>Answer</hi> unto them.</p>
                  <p>Sent from Mr. <hi>Bowles</hi> (Chaplain to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi>) to a Friend of his in LONDON.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Published according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand, July</hi> 11. 1645.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:3"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152964:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>JƲLY</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot to expresse my own aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctation, or satisfie others curiosity, but in love to Truth, and this Army, both which are sometimes abused by the frivolous and contradictory accounts, given by the Higling Diurnals, who are resolved, true or false, good or bad, to make up their Sheet. I have perswaded my self to this trouble, well knowing the perplexity of such an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, wherein the opinions and reputations of so many are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and the unpleasantnesse of it, when the variety of successe shall make me a Messenger of ill tidings: But that God may have the honour of what he doth for us, and by us; and that men, for want of a true and impartiall Information, may not fall out with the Instruments of their own good, I shall proceed.</p>
                  <p>After that it had pleased God in the midst of our enemies despight, and friends despair, to look upon us, and use as Instruments of his Justice upon an enemy fill'd with sin and pride; and of his Mercy to this Nation, in the late Victory at <hi>Nablesby</hi>-Field, which he was pleased to crown with the speedy and happy regaining of <hi>Leicester,</hi> which should teach us not to judge of any thing too soon, but wait for the counsell of God, which hath since made it appear, that <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> was lost, that both God and this Kingdom might gain by that losse. The Army marched toward <hi>Warwick</hi> solicitous in nothing so much as which way they might best serve the Publike: And being very doubtfull, whether it were better to follow the King, and hinder his recruting, or go down to the West, to relieve the other part of our Army, who had well deserved it, and long expected it; Letters were sent to the Parliament and Committee of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, declaring our indifferency, and willingnesse, to be swayed by their advice and resolutions, but not willing to lose any time, we marched on to <hi>Marlborough</hi> with a disposition, either to go over at <hi>Gloucester</hi> toward the King in <hi>Herefordshire,</hi> or to move Westward, and joyn with Col. <hi>Massey</hi> in the Western businesse; for though we knew he would adventure, and do as much as any man, with such a strength; yet the enemy being in common report 12000, and he but little above two, it was thought, that <hi>Goring</hi> might both keep off him, and keep up our men about <hi>Taunton.</hi> Having therefore recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved notice from the Committee of both Kingdoms, that Letters were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152964:4"/> sent to the <hi>Scottish</hi> Army to advance toward <hi>Worcester,</hi> and that we had their consent, and the Horses likewise, to march Westward, we bent our course that way; having yet so tender a consideration of <hi>Gloucestershire,</hi> that we sent Colonell <hi>Butlers</hi> Regiment to lie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Barkley</hi>-Castle, to keep in Sir <hi>Charls Lucas</hi> while the <hi>Gloucester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire</hi> Troops might look to the security of that part of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey beyond <hi>Severn.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After we had rested the Lords day at <hi>Marlborough,</hi> we mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from thence toward <hi>Amsbury,</hi> fourteen miles distant from <hi>Marlborough.</hi> This day being the Fair-day at <hi>Marlborough,</hi> occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the stragling and stay of some of our Souldiers, who were surprized by Souldiers from the <hi>Devizes,</hi> commanded by Major <hi>Dewet,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Runagado, lately wheel'd off to the King, whom as we hear, some Troopers under the Command of Major <hi>Buller</hi> have lately followed. We lost some men there, if it be a losse to leave such men, as leave their Colours. But that we might not be wholly beholding to the enemy for the execution of justice upon our strag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, one was hang'd that night at <hi>Amesbury,</hi> for going from his Colours, and endeavouring to seduce another. From <hi>Amesbury,</hi> the first of <hi>July,</hi> we marched by the way of <hi>Wilton</hi> to <hi>Broadchalk</hi> and <hi>Burchalk,</hi> 12 miles, where some of us passing through <hi>Salisbury,</hi> took notice of the Club-men, as we call them: Associates they term themselves, of whom a further account presently. They wear white Ribbands in their Hats, with <hi>Peace and Truth</hi> interwoven. They have forbidden the Souldiers of the adjacent Garrisons of <hi>Langford</hi>-House and <hi>Falston</hi>-House, to fight in <hi>Salisbury;</hi> but to be drunk together, is a small fault in the Cathedrall Calendar. They allow those two Garrisons contribution for the present; for which, one Master <hi>Hollis</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> is Treasurer, and hath a great influence upon this heap of men.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Broadchalk</hi> we marched <hi>July</hi> the second to <hi>Blanford,</hi> a Town noted for Malignancy; in our march a Dragooner was hanged for robbing a Countreyman upon the High-way. At <hi>Blande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> there was accidentally a Barn fired, which raised a mutuall jealousie betwixt the Souldiers and the Town, that it was done on purpose; But the Townsmen finding themselves enriched by the Souldiers lying there, began to be perswaded into a better opinion of the Parliament-Forces, against their wills. This night came to us Colonell <hi>Massey,</hi> and acquainted us with his strength and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and with a quarrell betwixt his men and the Club-men, at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152964:4"/>
                     <hi>Sturmister,</hi> in which the Club-men were reduced to reason at the last.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Blandeford, July</hi> the third, we marched to <hi>Dorchester,</hi> a Town as famous for piety and good affection, as the other for its aversnesse to good; But divers of the best Inhabitants being forced from it, the beauty of the Town is much impaired, and many houses empty.</p>
                  <p>In our passage from <hi>Blandeford</hi> toward <hi>Dorchester,</hi> came to us four Agents from the Club-men of <hi>Dorsetshire</hi> and <hi>Wiltshire;</hi> the chief speaker was Master <hi>Hollis</hi> of <hi>Dorsetshire,</hi> Brother to him of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Their businesse was to procure a Passe from the Generall for these persons to go to the King and Parliament with Petitions.</p>
                  <p>To the King were to go, Doct. <hi>Henry Goche</hi> (a Gentleman subject to mistakes, when he took the Manciples daughter of <hi>Trinity-Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> instead of a Wife; but made it good afterward in taking her to Wife) and Master <hi>Thomas Browell,</hi> Divines; <hi>John</hi> St. <hi>loe, Peter Hoskins,</hi> Esquire; Master <hi>Thomas Young</hi> an Attorney, more eloquent then honest, and Master <hi>Robert Pawlet,</hi> Gent.</p>
                  <p>To the Parliament, Master <hi>Melchisedech Woltham,</hi> Master <hi>Richard Hook,</hi> Club-Divines, <hi>Thomas Trenchard, Robert Culliford,</hi> Esquires; <hi>George Haules, Richard Newman,</hi> Gentlemen.</p>
                  <p>Master <hi>Hollis</hi> was pleased to deliver in the Petitions so to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, as also the Articles of Association. The brief account of both is this.</p>
                  <p>The Articles are,</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="articles">
                              <p>THat the Associates provide Arms, Set Watches, Be quiet with them that are so; Lay hold on disorderly Souldiers; Bring them to the next Garrisons; Not to refuse Quarter and Contribution to their ability, till their Petitions be delivered; Not to favour either Party; Or to protect any not Associated.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>The Heads of the Petions are, To</hi> desire a renewed Treaty, with a Cessation; <hi>as also,</hi> That the Garisons of <hi>Dorset</hi> and <hi>Wiltshire,</hi> be put into their hands, till the King and Parliament agree about their disposall: That they be free from all Charge, but the maintenance of those Garisons: That all Laws not repeated, be in force, and executed by the ordinary Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers: That all men who desire it, may lay down Arms; and others, who have absented themselves from their dwellings, may have free liberty to return, and live at home.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152964:5"/>
                  <p>After much speech had with them, and some consultation what to do in the businesse, it pleased the Generall to return his Answer in writing to this purpose.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ALthough the Paper brought to me, being not subscribed, cannot chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any Answer; yet, to clear my self from any aversnesse to the satisfaction of the Countrey, who are pretended to be interessed in these Petitions; I return this:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That my affections, and the aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ctions of this Army, are as much enclined to Peace as any mens whatsoever; and we undertake the War for no other end then the establishment of a firm and happie Peace, by opposing the enemies thereof: and that I shall be ready, so far as concerns me, to further all lawfull and fit means to procure it.</p>
                        <p>But having seen the Petitions for the conveyance of which a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe is desired, I must professe my self not so well satisfied with some things contained in them, as to concur to their delivering by any act of mine.</p>
                        <p>In particular, that a <hi>Cessation</hi> is desired, whilst, by Letters written by the King and Queen, taken at the late Battel of <hi>Naseby,</hi> it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appears, that Contracts are already made for the bringing in Ten thousand <hi>French,</hi> and Six thousand <hi>Irish.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is further desired, <hi>That the Garisons in these parts,</hi> whereof three are Sea-ports, <hi>should be delivered up to the Petitioners;</hi> which to grant, were for the Parliament to acquit part of the Trust reposed in them by the Kingdom, and (considering these forreign Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to run very great hazards to these Ports, to themselves, and the whole Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly, it is propounded, <hi>That liberty be given to all Souldiers to disband, and return to their home, if they desire it;</hi> which may with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall justice be desired by all parts of the Kidgdom; and so the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made unable to manage the War, before Peace setled.</p>
                        <p>These Considerations, with some other yet to be debated, will not allow me to grant the desire of the Letter.</p>
                        <p>But as for that part of the Petition which declares the grievances of the Countrey, by Plunder and violence committed, either by Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons or Armies; I do hereby promise and undertake, for the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and Armies under the command of the Parliament, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever Disorders are committed by them, upon a Complaint making known the Offences and the Persons, Justice shall be done, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction given. As also, I shall endeavour that the Parliaments
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152964:5"/> Garison<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> may be regulated according to any reasonable Agreement with the Countrey: and without doubt the Parliament will cause them to be slighted, so soon as the condition of these parts and the publike good shall permit: And that the Army under my command shall be ordered as may be most for the good and advantage of these Counties, and the whole Kingdom: of which, some reasonable testimony is already given, in their quiet and orderly passage thorow these and other Counties, without many of those complaints which usually follow Armies.</p>
                        <p>I further desire, That in the publishing this my Answer to your Request, all assembling the people to publike Rendevouz may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, and that Copies hereof may be dispersed to the several Parishes, that the Countrey may be acquainted therewith.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>THO: FAIRFAX.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>After the dispatch of these Club-Ambassadours (I leave it to other men to call them <hi>Knaves of Clubs,</hi> for I will not use my self to ill language) from <hi>Dorchester</hi> we marched toward <hi>Bemister,</hi> and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Army in the field betwixt <hi>Bemister</hi> and <hi>Crookhorn:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our march from <hi>Dorchester,</hi> we received notice of a sharp Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well (for so it proved) given by <hi>Goring</hi> at <hi>Taunton,</hi> wherein he spit his last venom, which our men received with their wonted courage. As also, we had notice of an Encounter betwixt the Governour of <hi>Lyme</hi> and the Club-men, about <hi>Bird-port:</hi> It seems the Club-men assembling, were sent to by the Governour of <hi>Lyme,</hi> who put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in a condition to receive the worst of Answers. To declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, they rudely tore his Papers, and increased their Sedition: Whereupon, he made toward them, to disperse them, which he did, with the losse of 50 or 60 Club-men, who it seems will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand Reason, till it be beaten into them. These Club-men were led by an Officer of the Kings: and we understand that <hi>Goring</hi> hath le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t them divers of his men to seduce them to disaffection and destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But we hope, if we may have some time and liberty, to quench this fire very shortly, though we were unwilling to stir it so long as <hi>Goring</hi> lay before <hi>Taunton;</hi> from whence, this evening of the fourth, we understand by Scouts from <hi>Taunton,</hi> and Prisoners taken at <hi>Crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,</hi> among whom a Lieutenant of Horse, that he drew off yesterday about noon, toward <hi>Ilmister,</hi> and this night is quartered about <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton:</hi> Our Army lying betwixt <hi>Bemister</hi> and <hi>Crookhorn;</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Mass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ys</hi> party betwixt <hi>Axminster</hi> and <hi>Chard;</hi> we having in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152964:6"/> these five days marched from <hi>Marlborough</hi> to <hi>Bemister,</hi> which is 62 miles.</p>
                  <p>On Saturday the fifth, having intelligence that the enemy was marched toward <hi>Somerton,</hi> we marched with the whole body to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Crookhorn,</hi> having sent early in the morning a party of 2000 Horse and Dragoons, under the command of Colonell <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> to discover the enemies motion, and take advantage of his Rere, if it were given. This party marched to <hi>Pedderton,</hi> alarm'd the enemy, and drove them first over to <hi>Pedderton</hi>-Bridge, then to <hi>Longlode,</hi> and so over that Bridge, which made the enemy face about, and bring up Foot, who, with the advantage of som Works formerly cast up, made good the Bridge against our Horse and Dragoons. After this a Brigade of Foot was commanded to march, their Quarters assigned at <hi>Crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn,</hi> which they obeyed most cheerfully, and advanced as far as <hi>Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derton:</hi> but they being extreme weary, and the night coming on, strong Guards were placed at the Bridge, and the almost-tired Horse drawn into their Quarters; it being a Countrey so full of strait pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, that it is very hard to engage an unwilling enemy, especially with Forces so harrassed as ours, with six days continuall Marches, and those long ones, saving the last, which the difficulty of the way made equally troublesom with the former. In this Chase, about ten prisoners of the enemy were taken, among whom a Cornet of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons.</p>
                  <p>Thus hath the Lord graciously led us to the end of this week, and enabled us to say, <hi>Hitherto hath the Lord helped us.</hi> It remains onely that he be acknowledged in all our ways, that he may direct our paths.</p>
                  <p>This sixth of <hi>July,</hi> our Head-quarter is at <hi>Crookhorn,</hi> where its possible we may rest a day or two, but not be idle. And we account it a mercy that the Lord hath so disposed of our affairs, that we have had liberty rest and wait upon him three Lords-days together; at <hi>Warwick, Marlborough,</hi> and <hi>Crookhorn,</hi> which have been the onely days of rest we have had since we came from <hi>Leicester.</hi> The enemy yet continues on the East side the River, which he lately passed at <hi>Lode</hi>-bridge, upon which they have three Garisons, at <hi>Bridgewater, Langport,</hi> and <hi>Ilchester:</hi> But we hope that God will direct us by his good providence, to such course as may be for the good of these parts, and the whole Kingdom.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From Crookhorn,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 6.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>An Exact and Perfect RELATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE Army under the Command OF Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the sixth of this instant <hi>July,</hi> to the eleventh of the same.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is expressed the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the VICTORY obtained by by the PARLIAMENTS Forces, over <hi>Goring,</hi> neer <hi>Langport</hi> in <hi>Sommersetshire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dated at Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> Quarters at <hi>Middlesey,</hi> 4 Miles from <hi>Bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, July</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Published according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand, July</hi> 14. 1645.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:7"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152964:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>JƲLY</hi> 7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the relief of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and our marching to <hi>Crookhorn,</hi> where we rested the Lords-day, <hi>July</hi> 6. Although our long march, and the wants of our Souldiers challenged some refreshment, yet the Generall, and the rest of the Officers, could not with patience endure an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my so near us; and therefore the party from <hi>Taunton</hi> were sent for, who came to <hi>Pedderton</hi> that night, Colonell <hi>Massey</hi> about <hi>Ilmister:</hi> The Generall seeing it very hazardous to free a passage at <hi>Longlode</hi> or <hi>Ilchester,</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Evil,</hi> thinking to passe the River there, or at <hi>Mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>-Bridge. A little before our coming to <hi>Evil, Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone</hi> men had broken the Bridge, which was presently made up; but as it fell out, we had no use of it, for the Enemy quitted <hi>Ilchester,</hi> a Garrison of theirs, and left us free entrance on Tuesday, where we quartered on Tuesday night. Little of moment fell out these two dayes, <hi>Goring</hi> dancing from one side of the River, to the other; so that our Officers that came from <hi>Taunton,</hi> had the more free liberty to congratulate our happy succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; ours at <hi>Naseby,</hi> which was a complete victory, their's at <hi>Taunton,</hi> which was more then a deliverance; for they continually affronted the enemy, took from him 400 Horse at severall times, and ordinarily made bold with their Guards. The poor Souldiers were much afraid, in regard of our delay of relief, that they should have had another <hi>Cornish Hugg,</hi> as they call'd it, but it pleased God to prevent their fears, by this seasonable Mercy.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152964:8"/> They lost a Gallant man, Colonell <hi>Floyd,</hi> a Religious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Souldier, and Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Richbell,</hi> a stout honest man, and some few Officers besides; some that were hurt, are recovered, as Major <hi>Marshall,</hi> Major <hi>Read</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This day Colonell <hi>Butlers</hi> Regiment, commanded by Major <hi>Fincher,</hi> Quarter-master Generall of our Horse, came near us, and in its march from <hi>Barkley</hi> Castle to us, did very good service. First at <hi>Dursl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y,</hi> they entertained Sir <hi>Charls Lucas</hi> coming to beat up their Quarters, kill'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Captain of the Forlorn-Hope, after that, charg'd the Party with two Troops, kill'd ten, whereof two Captains, took 39 prisoners, hurt Sir <hi>Charls Lucas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From thence they came to <hi>Highworth,</hi> where the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from <hi>Farington</hi> had entered the Town, whom he beat out, and delivered to the Governour, the quiet possession of his Garrison. From thence to the <hi>Devises,</hi> where they took some Horse, and so to <hi>Dorchester,</hi> where they over took some of <hi>Sherborne</hi> Horse; and so came to us very seasonably, being through Gods providence, neerer an engagement then we expected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wednesday, July</hi> 9. We divided our Force, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look'd the danger through our earnestnesse to discover and dislodge <hi>Goring;</hi> but the danger of division was the lesse, in regard that Colonell <hi>Massey</hi> had many Dragoons, at least 2000, and an inclosed Countrey: Whereupon Col. <hi>Massey</hi>'s party, with the addition of Col. <hi>Pyes,</hi> and Col. <hi>Sheffeilds</hi> Regiments, and all our Dragoons, but one Troop, were sent on the other side the Water, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Taunton</hi> and <hi>Langport,</hi> to amuse the Enemy, and take advantages, if he might; which he very diligently did, and came upon a strong Quarter of the Enemies about <hi>North-Curry,</hi> took them before they were well ready: charged, took 9 or 10 Colours, 4 Captains, some
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152964:8"/> Lievtenants and Cornets, and about 200 men, and more Horses; with very little losse, onely Col. <hi>Cook</hi> shot in the face, and Col. <hi>Buller</hi> hurt in the arm. We were not idle on the other side, but skirmished at a Passe a mile from <hi>Langport,</hi> took one Colours, which led the way to many more the next day.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Wednesday</hi> night, we quartered at <hi>Long-Sutton,</hi> and on <hi>Thursday</hi> morning, the tenth, a <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Warre</hi> was called, whether to draw up before <hi>Langport,</hi> and do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as opportunity might be, or withdraw toward <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> to refresh our men, and receive our sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Arms, Money, and Ammunition, coming to us by Sea; but it pleased God to end the businesse by an Alarm given us, that the Enemy had possessed the Passe we formerly skirmished at in <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ssebury</hi>-Bottom, and some of their Foot appeared on the Hill: whereupon, the Forces we had on this side the River, were drawn forth: Of Foot, <hi>Weldens, Herbarts, Inglesbies, Fortescues,</hi> Maj. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, <hi>Russels, Hammands,</hi> and <hi>Rainsbroughes</hi> Regiments, with Sir <hi>Hardre Wallers,</hi> &amp; the Pikes of the Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erals, <hi>Mountagues</hi> and <hi>Pickerings</hi> Regiments. The Muskettiers of those three Regiments together, with Col. <hi>Iretons</hi> Regiment of Horse, being sent on Wednesday night to the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of <hi>Massey.</hi> All our Horse, but the three Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sir <hi>Robert Pye,</hi> Col. <hi>Sheffeild,</hi> and Col. <hi>Ireton,</hi> and <hi>Okeys</hi> Dragoons, who were all with Col. <hi>Massey,</hi> but one Troop. With these, we drew into the Field, about 10 of the Clock on <hi>Thursday,</hi> and about 12 or near one, we began to dispute the Passe with them; the Enemy had a Hill, and the Winde, we another Hill, they had the Passe and the Hedges lined before we came; we drew up our Canon, which did us very good service, and made the other side of the Hill so hot, that they could not come down to relieve their men; presently, the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn-Hope
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152964:9"/> were commanded down to cleer the Hedges, which they did, seconded with <hi>Weldens</hi> Regiment, which was next them.</p>
                  <p>I need not say any thing of the General and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-General, who carried themselves according to their wonted diligence and gallantry.</p>
                  <p>The enemy had but two Pieces of Ordnance, small ones, having sent the rest, with most of their Carriages, to <hi>Bridgewater.</hi> The Passe being gained, the Horse went on. Major <hi>Bethel</hi> had the honour of the first Charge of Horse, who did it very gallantly, charging a Body of the enemy with a Troop, disordered them; and being over-born with a fresh Body, retreated slowly a little way, to Major <hi>Disbrough,</hi> who commands the Generals Regiment of Horse, where he rallyed, and charged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and they with him, and put the enemy to a foul Retreat, which they never recovered. Part of their Foot, with some Horse, and their two Pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, retreated into <hi>Langport,</hi> of which you shall have a further Account presently. The rest Horse and Foot, as fast as they could, ran toward <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> except some who scattered themselves into Corn and Woods for their shelter. Those that went toward <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> were earnestly pursued by our Horse, so that none of their Foot, recovered <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> and very many of their Horse, and divers Colours. The General and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General staying with the Foot neer <hi>Langport,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the enemy drawing over at <hi>Langport,</hi> and going toward <hi>Bridgewater</hi> on the other side of the River. Whereupon, we found the enemy had quitted it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, as they say, the Governour refused to hold it without 800 men, which they could not spare: and for a farewell, they fired the Town, to run away by the light. Hereupon, we marched into the Town with Horse, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152964:9"/> some Foot, who thorow fire and water, pursued on that side the River. With those Horse went Lieutenant-General <hi>Cromwell</hi> and Colonel <hi>Greaves,</hi> who overtook their Foot-Colours, and Ordnance, and three loads of Ammunition, which they brought back to <hi>Langport.</hi> The Horse, some of them, got to <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> some to a little Garison call'ed <hi>Burrow-Church,</hi> in the way betwixt <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> and <hi>Bridgewater.</hi> The General in the mean time marched on with the rest of the Foot toward <hi>Bridgewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for the advantage of Quarters, not being willing to stay in that wasted place, and came that night to <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey,</hi> four miles from <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this Fight, the whole Foot of the enemy were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spersed, killed, and taken; but few killed, thanks to hedges and heels. What Ordnance they had, were lost, and many of their Colours taken. I cannot give a more perfect account of Prisoners: Two Colonels of Horse, <hi>Slingsby</hi> and <hi>Heveningham,</hi> are taken, with <hi>Bertridge</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-General of their Ordnance, besides some Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-colonels and Majors; and, as I hear, about 1200 Prisoners: and this a very cheap Victory, we having lost no Officer, and not 20 common Souldiers, for ought. I can learn: Some of Major <hi>Bethels</hi> Troop are sore hurt, himself shot in the right hand.</p>
                  <p>Thus hath the God of our Salvation protected and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spered us, besotting the enemies old Souldiers, that they should suffer themselves to be engaged contrary to their intentions, and in the midst of their expectation of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to make up a formidable Army, directing us by his good providence, in the midst of our irresolutions: His Wisedom was our counsel, his Strength was our Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; let the praise be his. Our Word was, <hi>God with us;</hi> and he made it good: Theirs was <hi>Bristoll,</hi> which they will make good, its like, and run from <hi>Bridgewater</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152964:10"/> Many of their men came running over to us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such as <hi>Gerard</hi> had taken prisoners in <hi>Wales,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained; which should make us more carefull in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the enemies prisoners: and if it be not carefully heeded, it may be justly believed, that, notwithstanding the Covenant (the frequency of oaths having brought them to a formality, and Perjury being now grown fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar; which it were to be wisht were better thought on) Many of the prisoners taken at <hi>Naseby</hi> we shall be constrained to fight with once again.</p>
                  <p>A little before this Engagement, Master <hi>Hollis,</hi> the Ambassadour ordinary of the Clubs, came to us with a second Petition in the behalf of those whom Colonel <hi>Ceely</hi> had taken prisoners at <hi>Lyme;</hi> That reparation might be given for the lives of some who were killed, and the liberties of others who were taken; otherwise very fairly they must betake themselves to the adverse party for justice. The General being going to the Field, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him to stay at the Quarter, and he should have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer at his return; which, God be thanked, we can give him, with Honour and Justice. The enemies remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are at and about <hi>Bridgewater;</hi> our Head-Quarter at <hi>Middlesey,</hi> where our Officers are consulting what is next to be done; for that is all the Question with us. <hi>I pray God resolve it, and direct us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>A CONTINVATION OF THE Proceedings of the ARMY under the Command of SIR Thomas Fairfax: From the eleventh of this instant JULY, to the nineteenth of the same.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is added a <hi>Petition</hi> presented at a Rendevouz of <hi>Club-men,</hi> with their <hi>Queries.</hi> As also certain <hi>Observations</hi> upon their <hi>Petition,</hi> with a few <hi>Crosse-Queries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dated at Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Quarters at <hi>Chedsey</hi> neer <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> July 19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Published according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> July 26. 1645.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:11"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152964:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>JƲLY</hi> 11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the account which was given of the Fight and Rout on the tenth, all I can adde is, that <hi>Goring</hi> passed through <hi>Bridgwater</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> morning towards <hi>Barstaple</hi> without Ordnance, with three Carriages, about 3000 Horse, most of them unserviceable, 400 Foot, whereof 300 never came in the Fight, 8 remaining Colours, in a most perplexed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in regard of the discontent of his shattered Forces, &amp; the cariage of the Country, who made bold to bring up his Rear for him, which made him put 500 of his best Horse there to secure his march: as I am informed by one who marched with them; they have sent 500 Horse into <hi>Cornwall</hi> to bring up more sheep to the slaughter, and Sir <hi>Iohn Barkley</hi> is as busy as he may in pressing men in <hi>Devonshire,</hi> where the Country much opposes his proceedings.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152964:12"/>
                  <p>On <hi>Friday, Iuly</hi> 11. The Generall marched to a Rendevouz of Horse and Foot from <hi>Midlesey</hi> to <hi>Weston-Common,</hi> two miles from <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> from whence we discovered, upon a hill on the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand a company of Country-men gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with White-flying Colours, <hi>viz.</hi> Sheets and apporns, to whom it pleased the Generall, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with many of his Officers to go: The Countrymen referred themselves to <hi>Willys</hi> to speak for them, and to give account of their meeting, which he said was for safeguard of their goods, and for peace, to which purpose he produced a Petition for a Treaty. At the same time appeared another Gentleman with a Petition drawen by some part of the Country about <hi>Wells</hi> and <hi>Shepton-Mallet,</hi> which this company disclaimed, as also the carriage of the Club-men of <hi>Dorsetshire,</hi> so that there is some danger that these reconcilers will fall out among themselves. The Generall told them he came to protect them from the insolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of war, and to further peace, by scattering the enemies of it, desired them to send in Provisions, &amp; they should be paid for them, and so we parted fairely, and the good people were so well satisfied, that they gave us a most dangerous volley of shot of a quarter of an houre long, of which many of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152964:12"/> us were more afraid then of the shot in the battell the day before; so they returned to their houses, we to our quarters, which were that night at <hi>Weston</hi> and <hi>Chedsey:</hi> And Colonel <hi>Massey</hi> was quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered on the other side the water, two miles from <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On <hi>Saterday, Iuly</hi> 12. We continued in our quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters refreshing our men as well as we could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mony, the want of which for three weeks last past hath occasioned many straights, and some disorders, which we hope will be remedied by the supply which is now comming from <hi>Lyme,</hi> but let there be no expectation of any justice or order in an Army, if the Common Souldier, at least especially of Foot be not payed, whose 8.<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. will but let him live; and that those men who cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and couragiously upon any accosion adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their lives for the preservation of other mens liberties &amp; estates, should want that poor pittance is very hard, which they will do, unlesse a set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led course for convoyes be taken, and the Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer residing in the Army have some money always ready for extremities; but this is an unpleasant subject. This day the Cornet of the Generalls Troop was slaine by a shot from the Town, as he was riding between the Guard and the Workes.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152964:13"/>
                  <p>The Generall, and Lieutenant-Generall, and some other Officers went after noon to view the Works, from whence they were saluted by a Canon-shot made by the famous Lady <hi>Windham,</hi> who bid the Trumpeter tell the General she could do no lesse, and if he were a Courtier he would do the like.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 13. We likewise rested at <hi>Chedsey,</hi> the head-quarter; glad that our businesse gave us liberty for a Religious rest, which we have of late been very happy in observing. In the afternoon came to us Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> who with his Dragoons, and the assistance of some Foot took in <hi>Burrow-Church,</hi> and with it 150 prisoners, who rendred themselves with their arms, and what they had; Their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours name was <hi>Greenham.</hi> The Generall caused it to be possessed by a Commanded party of Foot, till further order be taken.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Munday</hi> the 14. We began to think of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of our moving, and also the great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of taking the town of <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> if possible; which we find strongly fortified in regard of the advantage of the water drawn about it, and many Ordnance in it, <hi>Goring</hi> having left with them al his but the two we to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k from him. A Storme was thought on, and provision made accordingly: Col.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152964:13"/>
                     <hi>Floyds,</hi> and <hi>Fortescues</hi> Regiments sent over the water to joyn with Col. <hi>Massey,</hi> to whom Col. <hi>Birch</hi> was also come with his Regiment, and three other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments appointed for this side, with their reserves. But the thing being of so great importance to our Army, our Officers being very tender of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Army, and lives of their men, thought fit at least to defer it till more certain information might be had of the Works and Trenches, and more full preparation made: And therefore when they were almost ready to fall on, they were drawn off Munday night late, and returned to their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. This evening, through the great goodnesse of God, the Generall, and Lieutenant-Generall esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a very great danger by water, passing the River in a Boat, which was within two minutes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overturned by the violence of the Tide call'd the <hi>Eager,</hi> comming in upon them.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Tuesday</hi> morning Col. <hi>Massey</hi> came over to our quarters at <hi>Chedsey,</hi> where a Councel of War was called concerning the Town of <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> and resolved that we should go on in making all preparations, which if they proved so good, and our Intelligence cross'd not the hopes of prevailing by Storm, it was suddenly to be attempted, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to be blocked up. We have these two dayes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152964:14"/> taken some Vessels in the River, comming to, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> laden with Mault and Oats, and such provisions: Six Vessels have been taken by us (in all) since our comming hither.</p>
                  <p>Oh <hi>Wednesday</hi> and <hi>Thursday,</hi> Preparations were diligently made for an attempt upon the Town: but finding it to be a thing of so great difficulty, the Ditch encompassing the Works, fil'd with water, being about six yards wide, and the Town well furnished with men, and having the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of so much warinesse given us by other Armies; It's thought it will not be expedient to put it to such a hazard: but rather, since there is some probability of starving it in a little time, to spend some patience upon it, considering it is a Town of so great importance to the welfare of the West, and withall considering that the blocking up this Town shall not be a totall impediment to other kind of action, as we hope the next Week will demonstrate.</p>
                  <p>As for the Intelligence we receive, it tels us that the <hi>Prince,</hi> and his Governour <hi>Hopton,</hi> are gone toward <hi>Cornwall</hi> to try their old refuge; which begins to be exhausted: and <hi>Grenvile, Berkley,</hi> and <hi>Gooring</hi> are busie, though to little purpose, in <hi>Devonshire.</hi> And lest this Intelligence should not be true, we shall very shortly send to know either how or what they do.</p>
                  <p>This day, being <hi>Saturday</hi> the 19. A party of Horse is sent toward <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndon</hi> to meet and bring up Recruits: and the Generall, and the rest of the Officers are in the Field neer the Town, setling quarters, to block up the Town to the very Works, or taking some quicker resolution, that the Army may be at liberty to be disposed of as may be most for the service of the Kingdome.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Chedsey</hi> neer <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water,</hi>
                        <date>July 19.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="petition">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152964:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Kings most Excellent MAJESTIE,</hi> And to the Right Honourable Lords and Commons of Parliament, Assembled at <hi>WESTMINSTER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE the Gentlemen, Free-holders, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all Protestants, and peaceable Subjects of the Countie of <hi>Somerset,</hi> Beholding with unexpressible affliction of our soules the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and terrible shakings of that well-built state of <hi>England,</hi> which our wise and carefull Fathers left unto us, that their Generations after them, under the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God, might keepe it up for ever; Are most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble suitors to your sacred Majestie, and to the said Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lords and Commons, that our so long and much tottering Kingdome may speedily be reposed upon her firme foundation, which we conceive to be the full and free convening in Parliament, of your Majesties Royall Person, and of all the Lords, together with the Commons, as well all them which have beene heretofore duly elected to this Parliament, and doe yet survive, as others who ought to be so elected thither, to fill all places in it made voyd by death: Your Majesties Royall and famous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors and Predecessors, the Kings and Queenes of this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152964:15"/> Land, invironed with this their full and free multitude of Councellors from all parts thereof, having ever been that Rock of safetie, whereon the good providence of God, for so manie hundred yeares past, hath established this Realme, in despight of all former tempests that have bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten against it. Therefore in this, the greatest of all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver rose upon us, or our Ancestors, we cannot but with our inflamed devotions to God, deprecate out of all mens hearts all thoughts of saving us, rather upon some new made grounds then that old one, which God yet never suffered to faile us, or of limiting our refuge but to part of our Rock, when our advantage and hope must be the more, if we have the whole to helpe us: As the most glorious Bodie that is visible in <hi>England,</hi> is the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> so who can thinke it so perfect, who can hope to find it so strong, to worke for the honour, peace, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of <hi>England,</hi> as when it consists in full of its Royall Head, and all the other good Members thereof?</p>
                  <p>Now therefore, with the utmost intention of our soules, and with all ardencie of our affections, we kneele unto your Majesties Kingly wisedome, and to the wisedome of the said Honourable Lords and Commons, that for the speedie integration, both in Head and Members of this Bodie, which is the soule of <hi>Englands</hi> welfare, your Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it may graciously please your Majestie and the said Honourable Lords and Commons to send; they unto your Majestie, and your Majestie to them, to appoynt your severall, that is to say, your Majestie, your Majesties, and they their Commissioners, and to hasten them to meet, Treat, and agree of Time and place, when and where your Majestie shall be, with your Houses of Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, both of them in their beautifull fulnesse of all their Members; we most humbly beseeching, that no place may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152964:15"/> be thought for this purpose to be like <hi>Gideons</hi> Fleece, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the onely spot of <hi>England,</hi> that shall be capable of the dew of heavenly blessing, and that all the Land besides will be dry; or to be the onely place which shall be dry, when upon any other Townes or Citie God will give down his dew; and for the securitie, both of your Majestie, and the Honourable Houses in any place, we shall lay downe our lives, and that which is left of our estates, to your Majesty, for the Houses, and to the Houses, for your Majestie.</p>
                  <p>And that we and the whole Realme may no longer want the benefit of those Lawes, which are well knowne to us by the undoubted Seales, of King, Lords and Commons, upon them, and may not still starve and bleed our selves to death, for such as could not yet passe this three-fold Test; We humbly pray, that the comfortable streames of Justice, which have beene so long bayed up, may be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all the Land, to refresh it, now everie where weary and weake, by the long impunitie of all sorts of sin and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie, and that Judges and Officers may be authorized to, and secured, in their administrations of Law and right to all people; And that all Field-Armies may be dissolved, all controversies for which they have beene raysed being layd downe, to be awakened and determined, or to sleepe and dye undecided in the full and free Parliament; And that all unnecessarie Garrisons be slighted, and such as shall be thought necessarie, either by your Majestie, or the said Honourable Lords and Commons to be continued, to be trusted in some hands of those Counties wherein they are sited, the Trustees to be equally named by your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, and the said Honourable Lords and Commons, and no Trustee to deliver up his Charge, but by the joynt Warrant of King, Lords and Commons in Parliament; and everie such Garrison to be maintained at the charge of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152964:16"/> the Countie where it is, untill we may see that happy day when the King, Lords and Commons shall declare, that there is no more use of any such warinesse betweene the King and his people.</p>
                  <p>And we beseech your Majesties Princely Clemencie, and the fatherly and fraternall love of the said Honourable Lords and Commons, to all their equall and inferiour Countrymen, for this sweet and necessarie condiscention to all that have beene in armes, or otherwise assistant on either partie to this destructive Warre, and to all that are imprisoned by any occasion of it, and to all that absent themselves from their dwellings upon feare thereof, that they may be permitted to returne home, and all men to enjoy their liberties and properties, and their wonted free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Commerce throughout the whole Realme.</p>
                  <p>Lastly, we most humbly beseech your Majesties most tender heart, and the feeling affections of the said Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lords and Commons, to their poore and bleeding Countrymen, to take notice of the manie importunate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitants, which have beaten us together into these our unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall meetings; not onely the worship of God, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Majestie, the native libertie and right of the Subject, the wealth and strength of the whole Land, and whatsoever is vertuous or laudable in it still suffering di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution; but also our intolerable slaverie, under a most insolent Souldierie; our universall povertie, by endlesse Contributions, and Plunders; the cursed Sacriledges done upon holy places, devoted to Gods service; the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous persecutions of Reverend Ministers, the manie tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Murthers and rapes that have beene acted, and more that are threatned upon peaceable Subjects, all sorts of wickednesse become everie where impudent and shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse; and in a word, whatsoever is dreadfull or miserable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152964:16"/> to us, is still growing upon us, under the Reigne of this Civill Warre: By all these so many and so power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full considerations, we having beene drawne together, as we contest the Searcher of all hearts, not for Sedition, but for the publique Peace, and in order thereunto, to meet together in this our humble Petition unto your Excellent Majestie, and the said Honourable Lords and Commons, and to put our selves into a generall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse, at the Crie of the Countrey, to pursue and arrest all Robbers and Murtherers, and all other Felons, under whose continuall Oppressions we could no longer endure.</p>
                  <p>Wee therefore humbly beseech your Majestie, and the said Honourable Lords and Commons, and all our supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour and fellow subjects of this Realme, that we may be mercifully and favourably judged in these our innocent intentions; and thereunto, according to our capacitie, and our wisest endeavours, wee dayly pray to the God of Peace and Love, that we may be revived, and the whole Realme, by a speedy and indissoluble Union of the strength and saving health of <hi>England,</hi> (next under his Heavenly Majestie) your sacred Majestie, the Right Honourable Lords, and the Honourable House of Commons, in a full and free, which cannot be but, a happie Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="questions">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152964:17"/>
                  <head>Some <hi>Quaere's</hi> presented by M. <hi>Willis</hi> at the Club-mens <hi>Rendezvous</hi> at <hi>Weston Common,</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Somerset,</hi> the last day of <hi>June,</hi> 1645.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. TO make choise of ten or twe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve sufficient men, such as are well knowne in their Countrey to be discreet and honest in the businesse we now meet about; that may endeavour with as much speed as may be, to present the Counties Petitions to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether it be not necessarie for us, who take up Armes for the peace of the Kingdome, to make choise of such men as we perceive and know to be of the ablest sort amongst us, for Judgement and Valour, to be Officers and Commanders, as Captaines, Colonels, &amp;c?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If it be agreed on to chuse Officers, whether such of the Parish as have Listed themselves, must not be tyed on paine of some penaltie, upon summons of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, with as much speed as may be to repaire to their Colours?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That such poore men as live by their dayly labour, course may be taken, by a generall Rate made once a Weeke by the chiefe of the Parish, to pay them for so many dayes as they have beene upon the generall imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which is agreed on by <hi>Dorsetshire</hi> Rate, 8 pence a Day.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Whether such as are able and knowne to be rich in the places where they live, and doe not yet, nor will not upon the next Summons professe themselves for us, and joyne with us in this good Worke, which is questionlesse acceptable both to God and all good men; whether they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152964:17"/> be not onely worthie to be accounted ill-affected to their Countrey, but also lyable to pay all such poore men as neglect their labour to doe their Countrey service?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Whether it be not convenient for all such men as be of abilitie, to provide themselves with as much speed as may be with Horse and Armes for the Service, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve themselves and the Countrey from violence, if any be offered?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What course to be taken for the furnishing of each part of the Countie with Ammunition.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Whether all such as prove themselves to be imprest men, and so forced on this unnaturall uncivill Warre, and they forsaking the Armies or Garrisons, and repaire to their homes, whether they may not, if they desire to stand for what we doe, be accepted?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. If any heneeforward be taken breaking an House, robbing in the High-way, stealing of Cattell or Horses out of our Grounds or Commons; whether that we, who stand to maintaine the Lawes of this Land, shall not give such the Law as they doe deserve, if the Governour next adjoyning the place, where the offence was committed, refuse to doe it?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Whether it be not necessarie, that the Countie adjoyning, repaire to the Governour of <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Passage-Boat of Commage, that the Westerne and Easterne parts may have Commerce and Trading to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and to passe either to other, as the Occasions of the Countrey shall require; and the like for <hi>Burrow</hi> Bridge?</p>
                  <p n="11">11. That if any man that is active in our Affaires, and takes more paines then ordinarie to bring our purposes to passe, be violently surprized by Souldiers on either side, to the losse of life or libertie; whether it be not necessarie for the whole Counties, to bind themselves by Oath either
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152964:18"/> to other, to joyne altogether as one Man, to avenge the abuse? For if this should not be, what man of estate or qualitie dares shew himselfe for us?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Whether any Gentleman of our Countrey, that hath beene or is knowne at this time to be active on either side, shall be, if they offer, accepted or no? considering, that if we admit them of one side, and not of the other, we shall prove partiall; and so, friends to the one side, and enemies to the other: and againe, if we accept of both, there must needs shortly thereupon grow a division among our selves; for that they which leave or come from the Kings side, will be drawing people their way; and they which come from the Parliament, will endeavour the like for the Parliament: and so the Wound of the Kingdome may prove more deadly then ever, and our last Rising be made the more incurable.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. That if sufficient proofe shall be made, that any Officer, or other person that joynes with us, or seemes of us, doe by any Plot, Stratagem, or Intelligence, endeavour to betray their Countries designe, or any particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in our Association, that he suffer death.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Whether it be not necessarie, that such Articles as shall be agreed on by this Countie for the good and peace of the Kingdome, be published in every Parish Church within this Countie; by the Parson or Minister of the Place, together with the foure Articles which <hi>Dorsetshire</hi> and <hi>Wiltshire</hi> have subscribed to? And in case any Minister refuse to doe it, that he be held as an enemie to us and the Peace, and so be proceeded against, as his offence shall deserve.</p>
                  <div type="observations">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152964:18"/>
                     <head>Briefe Observations upon the Petition.</head>
                     <p>ALthough all honest and wise men may be supposed to be sufficiently satisfied at the first sight of this Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet that knaves may be unmasked, and fools unblinded, it may not be amisse to take a little notice of it. First, the place of its conception was at <hi>Wels,</hi> a place of Episcopall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Parliament and Reformation, where it seems to have beene engendred by the malignant conjunction of the Lawyer and the Clergyman, which I am induced to beleeve, because there is so little of Religion or Justice in it: But howsoever it was begotten, the honester sort of Clubmen refused to owne it as legitimate.</p>
                     <p>But we need not take advantage of circumstances, the Petition bewrayes it selfe; first, in the Title, <hi>To the Lords and Commons of Parliament assembled at Westminster.</hi> And why not, <hi>To the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament at Westminster?</hi> Can it be though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that the Parliament are brought so farre below themselves as to accept of that appellation from an heap of people, which they refused to doe from that sacred Majesty so much extolled in the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</p>
                     <p>The first desire is, <hi>That there may be a full and free conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the King and all the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rds and Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ns in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The King since his departure hath beene often desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both by the Parliament and people to return, and hath as often refused. As for the Lords and Commons, as many as love Parliaments are there; for the rest, as they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, so they are justly absent: they were once rightfully called, they are now rightfully cast out for deserting or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying their trust, and to require their promiscuous re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, were to rob the Parliament of that power and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge concerning its owne Members, which most of the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> have protested to maintaine. As for the deprecations, they are confest to come from an infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152964:19"/> Devotion, it may be of some Priest in a Taverne; but such inflamations are dangerous. But in earnest, you depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate any thoughts of saving us upon any new made grounds. Me thinks you should rather have wisely avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded putting men in minde of new grounds, which it may be they never thought of, especially when your affection is so weake concerning the old one, which (you say) God never suffered to faile us. Alas, if it hath not failed us, why or how are all these things come upon us? You would not be saved by part of your Rock, as you call it. Wise and good men will not only be content, but glad to be saved by any means which God the only Rock thinks fit to use. Leave of deprecating, it is but saying your prayers backwards.</p>
                     <p>The second, <hi>That Commissioners may be respectively ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the King and Parliament to agree of the time and place of this full Convention.</hi> This seems but an unequall motion, that we should acquit a Parliament lawfully called, and by a further speciall Law continued, for a meeting to be appointed we know not how, why, when, nor where by this irregular and uncertain Treaty. Now comes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deprecation, <hi>Humbly beseeching, That no place may be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ught to be for this purpose like Gideons fleece, the only spot.</hi> Must no place be fixt upon? what can that meane, unlesse this, That to meet to no purpose, the fittest place is no where? Yes Gentlemen (for I suppose you pretend to be so that drew the Petition) we know your meaning by your mumbling, you would have a Parliament farther from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and neerer confusion, but Gods providence and their prudence have by particular Act setled them at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> whence they are not to be removed but by their own consent, which when you have obtained, that part of the Petition is answered. But the Parson might have made better use of his Bible then to produce <hi>Gideons</hi> Fleece to this purpose, though it appeareth that his wits were on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152964:19"/> wooll-gathering, yet he might have thought of some other Fleeces in his owne flock fitter for this Parable.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, tis desired, <hi>That the benefit of known Laws may still be reaped.</hi> So it is where it may, and most plentifully in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster-Hall,</hi> where those Judges who love Lawes better then Lusts still continue to dispence Justice under the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and protection of the Parliament. But it must be considered, that till the Sword is sheathed (which is ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly prayed and endeavoured) a full and free execution of all Laws cannot be expected; as sometimes one mans house must be puld downe that the whole towne be not fired; one mans ground must be broke to stop an inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that might spoile a Countrey; so some Lawes must be broken that in Gods good time all may be kept; some mens Liberties and Properties must be interrupted, that the publike Liberty of the Kingdome, and with that their owne may be preserved. Heer's a sad Deprecation follows, <hi>That you may not starve and bleed to death for such as could not yet passe the threefold test of King, Lords and Commons.</hi> As for you that framed this Petition, its beleeved you are farre from starving, and drinke more then you bleed; but those that suffer and bleed in opposition to that faction whereof the King is pleased to make himselfe the head, doe it not so much for the obtaining of new Laws not yet formerly established, as for the conservation of Religion, Law, Liberty, and a Parliament already setled, which have beene almost desperately invaded by Injustice, Tyranny, Superstition, Popery, and violent Attempts against the Parliament. Of which the endeavours to engage first the Scotch Army, then the English Army in the North against the Parliament in 1641. The Kings comming to the House of Commons, His leaving the Parliament, Raising an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Making a Cessation and Peace with the bloody Irish, and then bringing them into <hi>England,</hi> His resignation of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152964:20"/> himselfe to the Queens Councels, His Contracts for French Forces, which latter most evidently appeare by his owne Letters; are too true and and sad testimonies.</p>
                     <p>The next request is, <hi>That Judges and Officers may be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized and secured in the administration of Justice;</hi> which is already answered; <hi>and that all Field-Armies be dissolved.</hi> That is something unreasonable, to have neither Warre nor Peace: there is some disorder in an Army, but there is more in confusion, which must necessarily accompany the dissolving of Armies before Peace be setled. It is further desired, <hi>That all unnecessary Garrisons be sleighted,</hi> and good reason; <hi>and those that remaine should be committed to men of the same Counties.</hi> I know not what the fruit of that would be, unlesse to make men odious among their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who hate Garrisons and Governours And lastly, <hi>That these Governours be joyntly trusted by King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> When the King and Parliament agree about the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Garrisons, it is hoped they may agree about the government of the Kingdome; and till then things must rest as they are, or mend as they may.</p>
                     <p>In the next, His Majesties Princely clemency (graciously exprest to the Rebels of <hi>Irel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd,</hi> though constantly denied to English Subjects) and the Love of the Houses is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought, <hi>That all that have beene engaged in this destructive warre, or absented themselves for feare of it, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to returne to their wonted enj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yments.</hi> To give liberty to all Souldiers to returne to their dwellings were to ruine the Armies, and so to deprive the Parliament of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe that which they have so much right to doe, that is, to preserve the Kingdome; which is not to be done in this unhappy conjuncture but by force, when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is so dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerously infested by intestine enemies, and so dangerously attempted by forraigne preparations. And to proclaime promiscuous liberty to all persons, though never so highly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152964:20"/> guilty, to enjoy their freedoms, were in effect to say, That this Cause in quarrell, which hath cost so much blood, was certainly very sleight and unnecessary, it is so easily ended. It would be no wayes for the advantage of the Kingdome to have these wounds so skind over as to fester againe, but rather to be searcht and cleansed. The soundnesse and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines of every Common-wealth depends upon that which this Kingdome had more need be besought to, then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded from, <hi>viz.</hi> The equall and proportionable distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of Rewards and Punishments; not that rigour should be used towards the multitude misled by ignorance and passion, but that the safety of the Nation should be built upon the ruines of the malicious contrivers and active abettors of those designes that have brought this misery upon it.</p>
                     <p>Lastly, As for those importunate <hi>Agitants,</hi> as they are called, which have beaten you together into these unusuall meetings; I believe a stander by may see as much as a Gamester, and a stranger give as good an account as your selves, which may be to this purpose: First, It is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that the insolencies of Souldiers on each part, and the many unavoidable burdens, could do no lesse, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in the people a grievous wearinesse of their present condition, and a great readinesse to take any course that might help them, either in deed or in pretence: This ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage being espyed by the subtle craftinesse of some, who lye in waite to deceive; they diligently applyed themselves to draw people together, that so they might make those impressions upon them which were most suitable to their owne ends and interests, or else that the Country might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themselves to them who would expresse their owne Malignancy insteed of the peoples meaning; which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeares, in that many of the honest Countrymen refused to owne that which these contrivers would make
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152964:21"/> them speake. And as Malignancy and ignorance hath made up these meetings, so Justice and Truth must dissolve them, if this labour be not saved by that confusion and wearinesse which are incident to such disorderly and groundlesse un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings. As for the offence taken at the cursed sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges done upon holy places; It is acknowledged unfit that any incivillity should be used toward places by Law ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to publike Worship, (which Civill appointment is all the consecration that we can acknowledge) but it were to be wished, that well meaning people would begin to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that ignorant, id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, and unholy Ministers were the greatest prophaners o eir holy places, and that to take away the remnants or Idolatry and Superstition, as Crucifixes, Altars, and such like scandals, were not sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but Reformation. To conclude; the Petitioners may be assured, that the two great ends of these tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous assemblings, which are said to be the publike peace, and mutuall protection, may be more effectually advanced by sober and orderly proceedings, without attempting that which is both unreasonable and impossible, the reduction of all Civill and Military Power to their Propositions and Demands. If the Author may be thought to have discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red too much partially to the Parliament in this Answer, It is replyed, that he was driven to it by the inequality of the Petition, inclining as much on the other hand. For a conclusion, two things may be observed and amended in the affections and expressions of these Petitioners, <hi>viz.</hi> The little sense of Religion, which would almost induce a man to say, that God was not in all their thoughts when they went about it, as if they did not understand the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary conjunction of Truth and Peace, and the purity and Reformation of Religion, were the best foundations of outward happinesse. Secondly, The over deep sense of the calamities of war, without any reflections upon sinne,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152964:21"/> the cause of them; they speake as men resolved to have peace and plenty, without the taking notice of the God of peace: whereas we must know, that an humble submissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is more availeable to the removing of evils, then an impatient strugling. Let me not be so far mistaken, as to be thought to perswade a stupid couching under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: No, let all lawfull meanes be used; but let us take heed of promoting our ends, though never so desirable, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by unlawfull actions, as by stretching out our hands to a strange God, or with inordinate affections, when our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are warrantable. How much is it to be wished, that our uncircumcised hearts were humbled, and that we did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the punishment of our iniquity; Then would the Lord remember his Covenant, and remember the Land; That we could beare the indignation of the Lord, because we have sinned against him; then would he arise and plead our Cause, and execute Judgement for us: Till then, we shall but disquiet our selves in vaine, and by all our striving make our burthen more uneasie, and never a whit lesse unnecessary.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="questions">
                     <head>Crosse Quaeres to those of Master <hi>Willis.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the Title. Quaere.</hi> WHether the Clubmen ought not to bring Master <hi>Willis</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne punishment, for procuring and countenancing these illegall and unwarrantable meetings, seeing in the ninth <hi>Quaere</hi> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to maintaine the Lawes of the Land.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the first. Quere.</hi> Whether discreet and honest men will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake such a businesse as von meet about?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the second. Quaere.</hi> Whether, since Armes may be taken up for peace sake, why the Armes of the Parliament may not conduce as much to peace, as the Armes of the Clubmen? And further <hi>Quaere.</hi> Whether any who are fit to be Commanders, will take charge over them who are not fit to be commanded.</p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152964:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the third. Quaere.</hi> Whether the Clubmen will not quickly be as weary of their Commanders penalties, as of the Parliaments?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the fourth. Quaere.</hi> Whether the rates for the maintenance of poor Clubmen, are not like to prove almost as troublesome and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thensome as other Contributions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the fifth. Quaere.</hi> Whether this be not Club-tyranny? which if it must be endured, is more tollerable from a Prince then a Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant. And further, <hi>Quaere.</hi> Whether the worke be acceptable to God and good men, for it is not so questionlesse as is presumed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the sixth and seventh. Quaere.</hi> How they shall be able to keep themselves from being disarmed and disfurnished, when they have provided Arms and Ammunition, seeing a Clubman and his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e soon parted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the eighth. Quaere.</hi> Whether such imprest men, running from their Colours to their homes, may not be hanged, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the protection of this Association, especially if they be found out of their owne Country?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the ninth. Quaere.</hi> Whether it be not as unlawfull for the Clubmen to execute the Law, being not by Law allowed, as for the Souldiers to breake it?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the tenth. Quaere.</hi> Whether you can come at the Governour of <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> and whether he can come at the boate, being besie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? If the fiege be removed it is no question but you should.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the eleventh. Quaere.</hi> What power you have to impose an Oath, especially binding to vengeance, which belongs not to you?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the twelfth. Quaere.</hi> Whether any man engaged on the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments side will offer himselfe to your acceptance?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the thirteenth. Quaere.</hi> Whether the putting any man to death by <hi>Club-Law,</hi> be agreeable to the Lawes of the Land, professed to be maintained in the ninth?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To the fourteenth. Quaere.</hi> Whether the Minister can read your Articles, or whether he ought to publish these Articles, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the number of his Creed, or how you can punish a Minister without a Club-Bishop.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Quaere of Quaeres.</hi> Whether the Knave of Clubs was not Trump in all this dealing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>A CONTINUATION OF THE Proceedings of the ARMY under the Command of Sir Tho. Fairfax: From the ninteenth of this instant July to the three and twentieth of the same.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is related the particulars of the storming and taking the Towne of Bridgewater.</p>
                  <p>Dated at Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Quarters 23. Iuly 1645.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Published according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand.</hi> 29. Iuly 1645.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:23"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152964:23"/>
                  <head>The Proceedings of the Army under the Command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> from the 19. of this instant <hi>July,</hi> to the 23. of the same.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 19.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N Saturday afternoone, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, with the rest of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers met in the Field before the Towne, to prosecute their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of blocking it up, but it fell out, that in the midst of their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, the motion of storming was renewed, and in conclusion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on, to which purpose the preparations were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently hastened, and fitted for the time agreed on, which was Munday morning about two of the Clock, God graciously vouchsafing us the opportunity of a Sabbaths rest before so hard a labour.</p>
                  <p>The Lords day was spent in religious exercises by all those that could possibly be spared from the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites of so great a worke. This morning Sir <hi>William Courtney,</hi> a Colonell of Horse, shot and shattered in the thigh at the late fight, obtained leave of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (whose composition is courage and courtesie) to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152964:24"/> passe toward <hi>Winchester</hi> to see his wife and settle his affaires, having little hopes of recovery; he told us of Sir <hi>John Digbies</hi> death, who dyed in <hi>Bridgewater</hi> the day before of a shot in the arme, received neer <hi>Taunton.</hi> Toward the evening we drew into the field, neere the Towne, where the manner of the assault was ordered, <hi>viz.</hi> 600. Foot were to be drawne out of sixe Regiments, that lay in <hi>Chedsey,</hi> to assault the Towne in two places especially, 300. under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Lieut. Colonell <hi>Hewson,</hi> and 300. led on by Major <hi>Done,</hi> the sixe Captains were <hi>White, Price, Boys, Hill, Biscoe, Edwards,</hi> of each Regiment one. The Generals Regiment and the Major Generals were commanded by Colonell <hi>Hammond,</hi> who led them on as Reserves to the two commanded Parties. The Bridges fastened to Waynes, whereby they were to get over the ditch, was to be drawn in by the Officers of the Traine, with the help of the Firelocks and some other Souldiers that assisted them. And let me not omit, that Master <hi>Peters</hi> was appointed to preach to the Party that was to fall on, and did it <hi>tam Marte quam Mercurio.</hi> The Souldiers would not be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out, but freely offered themselves to the service: And so on Munday morning early the Generall, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generall, and the other Officers being all in the Field, our men fell on, and presently after the Bridges were laid, which was not done without some difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they entred the Towne with little losse; the most considerable person hurt was Lieutenant <hi>Martin</hi> of the Firelocks, who lost a leg by a great shot; we lost not above sixe or seven Souldiers, and had about forty wounded; wee tooke neare 500. Prisoners in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152964:24"/> towne, most of them Welchmen of <hi>Pembrokeshire,</hi> who were well disposed to the Parliament, and have taken up Armes for us 300. of them. Among the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners are a Lieutenant Colonell, called <hi>Pitman,</hi> a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, foure or five Captaines, nine or ten Lieutenants. The towne was strongly allarmd on the West side, but it seemes all things were not in readinesse with them to fall on, which if they had, we have very good grounds to believe, that we had carryed the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse, but let us be thankfull for the mercy God hath vouchsafed us in this, which is a good way to gaine the rest.</p>
                  <p>This day, the 21. we are striving to make good this part of the towne against the other, and it is a hot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute, not so much in regard of the Cannon, with which the Enemy plaies hard from the Castle, but in that the towne is fired, and in part burnt by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Fire-workes or Granadoes since the taking of it.</p>
                  <p>The Generall hoping that the storme might have wraught upon the Souldiers, and the fire upon the townesmen, so far, that they would have hearkened to a Treaty, renewed his Summons; which the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour peremptorily refused, according to his Allegiance, whether to the King or his wise, its doubted? Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Generall tooke up a double resolution of the highest Justice and mercy, and resolved for a second storme, but sent to the Governour an Answer to this purpose; That his denyall of faire termes had wrought in him no other thoughts then of compassion towards those innocent people that were like to suffer by the Governors obstinacy, which then that he might not be accessary to, he desired the Governour in his name, to give liberty to all the women and children to passe out of the town, that the rest who were more guilty, might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152964:25"/> abide the danger; the Governour accordingly made knowne his pleasure, which divers of the Ladies and other women gladly accepted, and the Lady Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, as she loves to be called, among the rest. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon some hot Slugs were shot in by a Souldier, and some other Fire works, which burnt some houses: We hoping the burning some might reduce them to a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley to save the rest; but as themselves confesse, divers in the towne put fire to houses, so that it was on fire in many places, and grew so hot in a little time, that it melted the Governour so far as to send <hi>Tom. Eliot,</hi> for so he is usually called, to excuse the holding out the town, to desire to know the Generals terms; He told them, he expected they should surrender to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: they returned these three Articles.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Governour, and all the Officers and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen that were in the Towne, with their Servants, Horses, Swords, Pistols, and Cloak-bags, might march with a Safe-Convoy to</hi> Exeter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That all the Souldiers might likewise march unto</hi> Exeter, <hi>leaving their Armes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That all Clergie-men in the Towne, and Townes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, may have libertie to march with us, or abide at their owne homes.</hi> Edmond Windham.</p>
                  <p>The Generall returnes these:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">Granted.</note>1. <hi>To all, their Lives.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>To the inhabitants their Liberties, and freedome from Plunder.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Neither Officers nor Souldiers to be Plundered of their Clothes upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The Gentlemen to be disposed of as the Parliament shall appoint, and in the meane time to have civill usage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Six Hostages to be sent, and an answer in a quarter of an houre.</hi> Tho. Fairfax.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152964:25"/>
                  <p>The Governour returned answer, that he found those Propositions so ill resented both by Gentlemen and Souldiers, that he could not accept of them: the Generall thereupon gave order to the Souldiers, to stand upon their guard, and goe to their dutie; M. <hi>Eliot</hi> desired nothing might be done till he returned, leaving Sir <hi>John Heale</hi> as Caution: Which was agreed to, and he presently returned, with an Answer of Submission to the Generals Articles; onely slipt in a Motion for himselfe, that he might have libertie to carrie the Newes to the King, upon his Paroll: May hee have more such imployment, till Peace be setled.</p>
                  <p>Thereupon the Hostages were sent, Sir <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hn Heale,</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Windham,</hi> Master <hi>Waldron,</hi> Master <hi>Warre,</hi> Major <hi>Sidenham,</hi> Master <hi>Speake;</hi> and we sent some into the Towne to them: The Towne was to be sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred according to the Articles the next morning at eight of the clocke, which was accordingly done: the particulars of all are not yet perfected; in grosse I may say, we tooke very many Gentlemen of the Countrey, Clergymen not a few, about 1000. Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, 40. peeces of Ordnance, 1500. Armes, and Powder and Match considerable, and a Garrison strongly fortified: That which may seeme to allay the happinesse of the successe was, that the towne was fired, but truly, though the strictnesse of Souldiery might very well justifie the action, yet God in his providence concurred to the justice of it, and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance. They refused treatie after part taken, they fired the part we had taken, and rang the Bells for joy, when they saw it blaze: and as we are credibly informed, they fired the towne themselves in many places, where fire-workes could doe no good; the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152964:26"/> souldiers, saying, the towne did it, to be rid of them; the towne, say the souldiers, did it, and the Lady com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it, when they were in little hopes to hold it. But God be thanked, we found much more of it stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then we expected. Some things there are which make the businesse very considerable; as first, it hath drawne a Line from the South Sea to Severne sea by <hi>Bridgewater, Taunton,</hi> and <hi>Lyme;</hi> it hath let loose our Armie for further worke, which is a mercie at this time of the yeare. It was a great gaine, with little losse: and that which addes as much to our satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as much as any thing, we kept our Articles; which is not onely honourable in the eyes of men, but accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the sight of God, and that which this Warre hath scarce formerly attained. It was done with some difficultie, in regard our souldiers had suffered so much, and <hi>Cornwall</hi> was so neere. But give me leave to adde to my Newes a motion, that is, that the soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier may have some encouragement beyond his Pay, for such services, that he may sometimes more then live; that their spirits may be held up, and they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to justice and honour. Thus doth the Lord follow us with mercie and loving kindnesse; let all whom it concernes, be humble and thankfull, and walke in love.</p>
                  <p>We are this night, the 23. returned to our quarters, the head quarter at <hi>Chedsey,</hi> and are meditating a day of Thanksgiving, mingled with seeking God for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther direction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Chedsey,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 23.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE ARMY Under the COMMAND of Sir Tho. Fairfax: From the foure and twentieth of <hi>July</hi> last to the one and thirtieth of the same.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is related the Surrender of <hi>Bath,</hi> and the state of our Army.</p>
                  <p>Dated at Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Quarters 31. Iuly 1645.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Published according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand.</hi> 4. Aug. 1645.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:27"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152964:27"/>
                  <head>The Proceedings of the Army under the Command of Sir <hi>THOMAS FAIRFAX:</hi> From the 24. of July last to the 31. of the same.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 24.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the entring of <hi>Bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water</hi> on the 23. Colonell <hi>Brick</hi> was desired to take (at least) the present charge of the Town, and the Commissioners for the Army were likewise ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to gather together all the goods of Souldiers and Gentlemen which were to be left by the Articles, and amounted to a considerable summe, as the owners say; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o make sale of them to raise Money for the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which might be not onely a reward for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152964:28"/> service past, but an incouragement to service and faithfull performance of Articles for the time to come: But we have reason to feare that we shall not raise a proportion in any reasonable time. This day and the 25. likewise we rested at <hi>Ched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey,</hi> disposing Prisoners and setling the affaires of that Towne. On the 26. we marched from those Quarters to <hi>Martock,</hi> where the head Quarter was, and some of the Regiments at <hi>Long-sutton,</hi> At <hi>Martock</hi> we rested the Lords day the 27. and made it a day of Thanksgiving, being willing to take that or any advantage to thankfulnesse, other daies allowing so little lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. As soon as we returned from the afternoons meeting, we had new matter of praise offered us from the Governour of <hi>Lyme,</hi> who sent an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the taking of <hi>Chadiock</hi> House, a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison that much annoyed <hi>Lyme</hi> and those parts; But its like a full account of those passages is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by others.</p>
                  <p>On Munday, it being found that the Army wanted many necessaries, and that upon a little stay the recruits might be come up, &amp; the whole Army disposed to the best advantage, till we were inabled to do the most considerable work,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152964:28"/> which may be supposed to be the following the Enemy, &amp; interrupting his endeavours of raising men, it was thought fit not to be wholly idle; whereupon the Army was divided, part sent to <hi>Sherborne,</hi> to block it up at least, and to take further advantages if suffered, whether went Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Pickering</hi> and the Controller of the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery: The other part marched with the Generall toward <hi>Bath</hi> good ground being given that that place might be easily reduced and made (if not a Garrison) yet a strong Quarter very advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the taking <hi>Bristoll,</hi> which is not yet ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any designe to be neerer laid, it being so much infected, that it is more like to take an Army then be taken by it.</p>
                  <p>We came on Munday night to <hi>Wells, Bona terra mala gens,</hi> there we heard that <hi>Bath</hi> was quitted or very neare it; and it seems their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was this, The Townesmen not willing to beare Armes, nor yet to receive Souldiers from infected <hi>Bristol;</hi> the Souldiers were too few to hold it, so that the Governour Sir <hi>Thomas Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> had quitted it, had not Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> sent about 100. men to him with orders to stay.</p>
                  <p>Upon hearing the probability of quitting it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152964:29"/> the Generall thought fit to spare his Foot any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary labour, and sent two Regiments of Horse under the command of Colonell <hi>Rich,</hi> and two Troops of Dragoons with Colonell <hi>Okey</hi> to give account of the condition of the towne, that Orders might be given accordingly. They came neere the towne on tuesday the nine and twentieth, which was held against them, and summoned; afterward they applyed themselves to see what might be done by force, the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons soone beat them from the Bridge, which being gained they set fire to a strong gate on the South-west, and when that was burnt the Governour and his Officers were willing to compound, and to obtaine their owne liberties of marching to <hi>Bristoll,</hi> left the place, and in it 130. common Souldiers prisoners, the rest running away in the time of the Treatie: ten, or, as some say, twenty barrels of Powder, three hundred Armes, a tunne of Match, sixe iron peeces of Ordnance: Whereupon two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments were drawne from <hi>Wells</hi> to take pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the towne till it be further setled. The Generall in person riding thither on Wednesday the thirtieth to see it done, where he received
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152964:29"/> Letters from Captaine <hi>Swaniey,</hi> that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken twenty Vessels lying on the Welch Coast to receive souldiers to be conveyed over to <hi>Ʋphill,</hi> and desiring some men to be sent into Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brokeshire to strengthen the Garrisons there against a destroying insolent enemy, who hath scarce any place but that left to execute his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty upon. And the Generall hath granted to send five hundred men which we have taken of that Countrey, who are very well affected to the Parliament, and willing to doe service.</p>
                  <p>The Generall is this last of <hi>July</hi> returning to <hi>Wells,</hi> he having left a Garrison in <hi>Bath,</hi> and so intending to go on to unite the Army, and receive the recruits and other necessaries, and hasten to what action shall most conduce to the publike.</p>
                  <p>Let us all be watchfull to give glory to God, who loads us daily with his benefits.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From</hi> Bath, <date>
                           <hi>July ult.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="proceedings">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:30"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152964:30"/>
                  <head>The Proceedings of the Army under the command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> from the first of <hi>August</hi> to the seventh.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>August.</hi> 1.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the taking of <hi>Bath,</hi> with which the last moneth was happily closed, the Generall gave order for the setling a Garrison there, so strong as that it might bee a check to <hi>Bristoll;</hi> whereupon Colonell <hi>Birches</hi> and Colonell <hi>Wallers</hi> Regiments of foot were ordered to remaine at <hi>Bath,</hi> and three Regiments of Horse. <hi>viz.</hi> Colonell <hi>Butlers,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Cooks,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Pophams</hi> appointed to quarter thereabouts, that they might joyne together for the block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up or straitning of <hi>Bristoll.</hi> The Generall returned this day to <hi>Wells</hi> to the rest of the Army.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Wells</hi> Aug. 2. we marched toward <hi>Sherborne;</hi> the head quarter was at <hi>Queene Carnell,</hi> but the Generall impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of staying there when he had forces engaged against <hi>Sherborne-Castle,</hi> which was but foure miles distance, rode away to <hi>Sherborne</hi> that night, and quartered at Master <hi>Kings</hi> house a Lawyer, who out of a needlesse feare of our Army betooke himselfe to the Castle, where hee was shot, and since died.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. The Lords day was kept at <hi>Sherborne,</hi> as we have hitherto, through Gods providence, constantly and careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done; onely the Leaders of the Clubmen interrupted our rest, being met at <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> the day before they were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152964:31"/> apprehended by a strong of Horse commanded by Colonell <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> who this day brought them safe to <hi>Sherborne:</hi> the number of them was about fourty, many scarce worth the naming, the most notorious and active were M. <hi>Young,</hi> M. <hi>Hoskins,</hi> M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Goche, Cradock</hi> of <hi>Blandford, &amp;c.</hi> of these more hereafter when the Examinations are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 4. On Munday morning, notice being given that the Club-men had appointed severall meetings, Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> was sent with foure Regiments of Horse to look after them, and to enquire an account of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As the Partee was marching toward <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> they discovered some Colours upon the top of a high hill full of wood, and almost inaccessible; a Lieutenant with a small party was sent to them to know their meaning, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them that the Lieutenant-Generall of the Army was there. Whereupon their Leader, Master <hi>Newman,</hi> thought fit to come downe, and told us, The intent was to desire to know why the Gentlemen were taken at <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> on Saturday. The Lieutenant-Generall returned him this answer; That he held himselfe not bound to give him or them an account; what was done, was by authority, and they that did it were not responsible to them that had none. But not to leave them wholly unsatisfied, hee told him, That those persons so met had beene the occasions and stirrers of many tumultuous and unlawfull meetings, for which they were to be tried by Law, which triall ought not by them to be questioned or interrupted. Master <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> desired to goe up to returne the Answer. The Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-Generall with a small party went with him, and had some conference with the people to this purpose, That whereas they pretended to meet there to save their goods, they tooke a very ill course for that, for to leave their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152964:31"/> houses was the way to lose their goods, and it was offered them that Justice should bee done upon any who offered them violence: and as for the Gentlemen taken at <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> it was only to answer some things they were accused of contrary to Law and the Peace of the Kingdome. The men were well satisfied and promised to returne to their houses, and accordingly did so.</p>
                  <p>After this the Lieutenant-Generall with his partee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to <hi>Hamelton-Hill</hi> neere <hi>Shrawton,</hi> at the bottom of the hill we met a man with a Musket, asked whither he was going? he said to the Club Army; what he meant to doe? he asked what we had to doe with that; being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to lay down his Armes, he said, He would first lose his life, but was not so good as his word, for though he cock't and presented his Musket, he was prevented, dis-armed, and wound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, but not killed. Then we marched up the hill, which had beene an old Roman worke deeply trench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Lieutenant Generall sent before, a Lieutenant with a partee of Horse to require an account of their meeting, he was answered with halfe a dozen shot, and could get no other Answer; thereupon one Master <hi>Lee,</hi> who upon our approach came from them, was sent in, requiring them to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the power and protection of Parliament, and lay down their Arms: They refused to leave their Armes, and gave us a shot as we were drawing up; The Lievt. Generall unwilling to bloodshed, sent Master <hi>Lee</hi> againe to tell them, that if they would not lay downe their Arms, he would fall upon them: They refused this third Message also, through the instigation of Master <hi>Bravell,</hi> Minister of <hi>Compton,</hi> who told them they must stand to it now rather then loose their Armes, and that he would Pistoll them that gave back.</p>
                  <p>Thereupon order was given to the Generals Troope to fall on; who did so, and received a repulse and some losse
<pb facs="tcp:152964:32"/> through the disadvantage of the place, for the Clubmen shot from the banke, and kept the passage with Muskets and other weapons, which was no broader then for three Horse to march in one brest: at this charge we lost a man or two, had eight or nine wounded, sixe or seven Horses killed; Then Major <hi>Disbrough</hi> with his Troope went round upon a ledge of the hill, and made a hard shift to climbe up and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on their reare, and then they ran, and the passage for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly assaulted was opened likewise, and all the Clubmen dispersed and disarmed; as we are since informed, sixtie of them killed; we brought away 400. of them to <hi>Shrawton,</hi> of which neare 200. were wounded. In this Skirmish Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Paltson</hi> a very gallant man was sorely hurt on our part, and about twelve more. We found among them about 16. of our men, whom they had disarmed and taken Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and threatned to hang some of them, but the Tables are turned.</p>
                  <p>We quartered that night at <hi>Shrawton,</hi> and kept the Club<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Church, and with them foure Vicars and Curates tooke with them upon the hill, but at no Divine Service I can assure you, whereof Master <hi>Talbot</hi> of <hi>Milton</hi> was one, and <hi>Lawford</hi> of <hi>Auckford</hi> the worst.</p>
                  <p>The next day <hi>August</hi> 5. we tooke their names, and their examinations, who were their leaders, and what the grounds of their meeting were, which they freely discovered, and confessed Master <hi>Bravell</hi> the Minister of <hi>Compton</hi> sent out the Warrants; and the intent was, as appeares by a Warrant from Master <hi>Rogers</hi> of <hi>Langton,</hi> gallantly to demand their Countrymen, or to take so many Prisoners as should release them (as the Warrant ranne;) and that they had laid downe their Armes and submitted, had it not been for <hi>Bravell</hi> and <hi>White</hi> and <hi>Lawford;</hi> and that they sent to <hi>Wiltshire</hi> men to come joine with them; whose journey is now stopt.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152964:32"/>
                  <p>After the Examinations taken, the Lievtenant Generall spake to them, giving liberty to defend themselves against plundering, forbidding any more such meetings; which they protested against, and freely consented, if any of them, whose names were in the paper, were taken againe opposing the Parliament, or in any such assembly, they deserved to be hanged, whereupon they were dismissed to their very good satisfaction, and confessed they saw themselves misled by their leaders, who by a pretence to save their goods, endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered both their goods and lives; and so we parted, and I hope shall never meet againe upon those termes: But wee finde their leaders extreamly partiall on the Kings side, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding their pretended indifferency, as appeares by <hi>Bravels</hi> activity since he was at Court with their Petition, and their calling men Roundheads that refused to joine with them, threatning no lesse then losse of goods, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of life to them that would not come: and this worke though unhappy, was very necessary, for we could send nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parties nor Messengers before, whereas now, a man may ride very quietly from <hi>Sherborne</hi> to <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>August</hi> 5. On Tuesday night we returned to <hi>Sherborne,</hi> where we found the Generall and the rest of the Army very busie at the siege of <hi>Sherborne,</hi> a malicious mischievous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, like the Owner; a Storme was intended, but upon se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts diverted; we see our recruits come so far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low expectation, both in time and number, that we must take more then ordinary care of our men, though the Army be now as strong as ever it was.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>August.</hi> 6. On Wednesday morning our earnestnesse to draw our Workes very neare betwixt the lodge and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle exposed us to some losse, which though not much, yet was more then all our late service, The Major and four Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Colonell <hi>Rainsboroughs</hi> Regiment being shot, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152964:33"/> two, <hi>Fleming</hi> and <hi>Horsey,</hi> were gallant men, are since dead; we hope well of the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>August</hi> 7. This day the Councell of Warre hath given or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for all possible diligence to be used toward the taking of this place before our recruits come up, and the Generall hath appointed a Commission to examine the leaders of the Club<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, so that there is some hope that this Malignant County may in time be reduced and reformed, especially if some wise and honest men of these parts would come downe and contribute their best toward the information and ordering the people, who are after their sufferings more capable of good then heretofore.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Devonshire</hi> we heare that <hi>Goring</hi> playes an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine game, and can scarce tell at the weeks end whether he wins or looses, some comming and some running; we had been with them before now but for our recruits and some other necessaries, and that it was not thought safe to leave the Clubmen and <hi>Sherborne</hi> Castle to perfect their designe, which was far advanced, but now, as we hope, not onely shaken but broken.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Sherborne,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>August</hi> 7.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152964:33"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>